Guide to the Ghassem Ghani collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ghassem Ghani collection
1800-1900
MS 235
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.5
(1 box, 2 folios)
A collection of Persian manuscripts dating from the nineteenth century and consisting largely of official correspondence and reports to the Shah of Iran.
Ghanī, Qāsim, 1898-1952
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cyrus Ghani, 1963.
Existence and Location of Copies
Series I-V and VII-IX are also available on microfilm (751 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University, at cost. Order no. HM25.
Arrangement
SERIES I
SERIES II
SERIES III
SERIES III - A The Letters of AmÄ«r Kabir from No. 1 to 210.
SERIES IV
SERIES V
SERIES VI
SERIES VII
SERIES VIII. ("Container No. 8")
SERIES IX
Scope and Contents
A collection of Persian manuscripts dating from the nineteenth century and consisting largely of official correspondence and reports to the Shah of Iran.
Manuscripts, Persian; Persian language -- Texts; Iran -- History -- Qajar dynasty, 1794-1925; Middle East
- Series I
  - 1. Haji Mirza Aqasi (chancellor of Mohammad Shah) to Manuchehr Khan Motamed-od-Dowleh (Governor of Isfahan) Concerning a dispute between Abdol Hosein Khan and Ibzahim Khan over agricultural property. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 2. Haji-Mirza Aqasi to Mohammad Shah (Shah of Iran). Concerning the conversation between Mirza Djafar Khan and Russian Prince Vorontzov. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 3. Same to Same. Assuring the Shah that there are no symptoms of any new disease in the Harem. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 4. Same to Same. Expressing sorrow that the Moslems are not concerned with the conquest and subordination of the nonbelievers. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 5. Same to Same. Prays that God may not remove the shadow of the Shah from the heads of the people of Iran. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 6. Same to Same. Concerning the Russian General Perovski and the chaos in the Persian army. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 7. Same to Same. In defence of a court official who was criticized by the Shah. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 8. Same to Same. Thanking the Shah for his concern over his health. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 9. Same to Same. Inviting the Shah to Abbas AbÄd for rest. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 10. Same to Same. Concerning his health. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 11. Same to Same. Concerning two letters written six years previously to two foreign envoys which were never delivered to them. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 12. Same to Same. Complaining about the brothers and the uncles of the Shah who are involved in intrigues and treason. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 13. Same to Same. Complaining about the foreigners (Europeans) who have caused him pain and suffering. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 14. Same to Same. A routine report. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 15. Same to Same. Concerning the necessity of the Shah's presence in the capitol. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 16. FarhÄd MirzÄto Bibi Jan. Sending a Koran to her. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 17. Koluke, Shah's physician, to the Shah. Concerning the mineral waters of Larsidjan. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 18. HÄji Mirza Aqasi to the Shah. Concerning some diseases in the city and the suburbs (of Teheran). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 19. Farhad Murza to Sepah-Salar Aáº"am: Concerning the mutiny of some soldiers and their punishment. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 20. A note by Farhad Mirza (then the governor of Teheran): Consulted Hafez (Persian poet whose verses are used for telling fortunes). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 21. Farhad Mirza to Assef-od-Dowleh: Complaining of sickness and old age. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 22. Mirza Abbas Khan Muaven-of-Molk: Inquiring after the health of Amin-od-Dowleh. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 23. Mirza Abbas Khan Muaven-of-Molk: Inquiring after the health of Amin-od-Dowleh. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 24. Hesam-os-Saltaneh-to Sadra-od-Dowleh: Confirming the receipt of a package of tea. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 25. Same to Same: Concerning his estates in Isfahan. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 26. Same to Same: Continuation of No. 25. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 27. Mirza Ussof Mostashar-od-Dowleh to Aqa Gafar (a merchant): Sending a money order for the price of a book. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 28. Safi Ali Shah to Abdol Ali Mirza: Confirming the receipt of a pair of glasses. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 29. Same to Same: Inquiring about his health. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 30. Malkam Khan to (addressee unknown): Criticizing the lack of security in Iran (dated July 26, 1906). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 31. A note by Farhad Mirza (dated 1295 A.H.). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 32. Egbal-od-Dowleh Kash?to Naser-os-Saltaneh: A routine letter. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 33. Safi Ali Shah to (addressee unknown): Concerning the survivors of Nosrat-os-Saltaneh who are in need. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 34. Abdul-Ali-Mirza to his daughter Zahra Khanum: Concerning the expenses of the house. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 35. Masud-Mirza Zell-os-Soltan (the Shah's son) to Saheb Ekhtiaz: Sending a gift. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 36. KÄmrÄn MirzÄto Saheb Ekthiar (then Minister of Justice): Asking him not to sign the court decision concerning Mohammad until he seems him. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 37. Hajib-od-Dowleh to Amin-od-Dowleh: Informing him about Naser-ed-Din's (the Shah's) arrival at Anzali. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 38. An envelope on which is written: "Two papers with the handwriting of Motamed-os-Saltaneh are presented". (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 39. Mutamed-os-Saltaneh to Gavame Hozuz (dated 1330 A.H.): Concerning a country estate. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 40. Mirza Ali-Asghar Khan Atabak (Chancellor) to the Shah: Complaining about the minister of War and his intrigues. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 41. Moshir-od-Dowleh to Azed-os-Saltaneh: Concerning the regulation of the army in Azerbaidjan. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 42. Amir Azam to Dr. Qizil Ayaq: Sending him 50 tumans. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 43. Ein-od-Dowleh to Dr. Qizil Ayag: Saying farewell before leaving Tehran. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 44. A table written by Sani-od-Dowleh: Some political, commercial and geographical information of different countries. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 45. The same: The comparison of the measurements of different countries. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 46. Abdul Hossein Farmanfarmaian to Dr. Ghani: Sending him the money for his bill. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 47. A letter addressing Nazem-od-Dowleh (Persian Ambassador in Turkey): Concerning postal exchange between Iran and Turkey. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 48. Fatholla Khan Sheibani (addressee unknown): Requesting a picture. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 49. Mohammad Hassein Foroughi: A piece of handwriting. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 50. Fatholla Khan Sheibani (addressee unknown): Greetings and compliments. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 51. Haji Pir Zadeh to Farhad Mirza: Greetings and compliments. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 52. Fatholla Sheibani to Haji Pir Zadeh: Thanking him for a picture and discussing the state of affairs in France. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 53. Addressee is Mirza Abdol Vahab Asef-od-Dowleh: The letter is written for Prince Navab Azed-od-Dowleh. Regretting that he cannot be present at a party. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 54. Dabir-ol-Molk to Amin-od-Dowleh: Informing him of his (Amin-od-Dowleh's) appointment to the chancellorship and the arrival of the Shah to Anzali. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 55. Mirza-Abol-Qassen (poet) to Farhad Mirza: Concerning the loss of several donkeys with loads of wheat. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 56. Reza Veqar (poet) to Farhad Mirza: Requesting the rent of a village. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 57. The same: Complaining of his illness. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 58. Reza Quli Hedayat: A list of the rulers of Mazanderan (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 59. Molla Nazar Talegani (a famous clergy) to (addressee unknown) Concerning a divinity student. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 60. Amir Kabir (Chancellor during the first years of the reign of Naser-ed-Din Shah to Nasir-od-Dowleh: Making an appointment with him. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 61. The handwriting of Mirza Hassan Ashtiani (a famous clergyman) on the margin of a letter concerning a judicial problem. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 62a. Farhad Mirza to the Persian Ambassador in Turkey dated 1298 A.H.: Concerning an article printed in "Akhtar" newspaper dealing with astronomy. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 62b. Hessam-od-Saltaneh to the Ambassador in Turkey: Greetings and compliments. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 63. Shams-ol-Ulema to Sarem-Lashkar: Concerning the sending of a sum of money on account of the harvest. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 64. Hosein Malik to Dr. Ghani: Sending him a piece of the handwriting of Malek-od-Tojar and two copies of Hafer. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 65. Malek-ot-Todjar to his brother, dated 1329 (A.H.) concerning their private affairs. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 66. Sayah Mahallati to (addressee unknown): Concerning the writing of a book. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 67. In Re Amir Kabir: Concerning an audience. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 68. Same. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 69. Same: Concerning the reception of the Turkish envoy and complaining about the harsh behavior of the Russian ambassador. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 70. Mirza Aga Khan Nouri (Chancellor) to the Shah: Holiday greetings (on the back of this letter the Shah's handwriting.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 71. In Re Amir Kabir: Private Affairs (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 72. The Same: Concerning Imam JumÄof Tabriz who had refused to go to the court of the Shah. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 73. Davar (then Minister of Finance) to Dr. Ghani, dated 131 [5?]. (A.H.) Concerning the receipt of the order. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 74. Davar to Ghani (1315 A.H.): Sending him two letters and requesting him to compare them with the letters in the library of Majlis (parliament) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 75. Vosug-od-Dowleh to Dr. Ghani: Thanking him for the receipt of a picture. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 76. The Same (dated 1309) (A.H.) New Year's Greeting. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 77. Farzin to Dr. Ghani: Concerning the sending of two packs of tea (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 78. Jiyyed Abdol-Ghani (Dr. Ghani's father) (addressee unknown): Concerning the hospital in Sabzevar (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 79. Haji Amin-oz-Zarb to Dr. Ghani (1308) (A.H.): New Year's Greetings. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 80. An entrance ticket into the Vatican in the name of Dr. Ghani (dated Dec.21, 1924) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 81. Mirza Said Khan (minister of foreign affairs) to the Persian Ambassador in Turkey: Concerning the personal relations. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 82. Hassan Ali Khan Amir Nezam to the Persian Embassy in Turkey dated 1289: Expressing his gratitude to the Sultan of Turkey for a gift and mentioning Shah's dissatisfaction with the scandal in Khan-Valedeh. (in Istanbul) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 83. Writer and addressee unknown: Remittance of two hundred tumans for Iranian Consul General in Egypt. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 84. Mohsen Khan to the Persian Embassy in Turkey dated 1279: Description of his arrival in Trapuzan. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 85. Mutamed-od-Dowleh to the Persian Ambassador in Turkey, dated 1298 (A.H.) Concerning the complaint of merchants about the Consul General in Istanbul. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 86. Zel-os-Soltan to Man-al-Folk, dated 1298 (A.H.) Concerning the complaints of the Iranian merchants about the Persian Consul General. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 86a. His?m Al-sult?n to Mu c?n Al Mulk (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 86b. Amin-os-Soltan to (addressee unknown) dated 1308 (A.H.): Concerning (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 86c. Amin-os-Soltan to Ala-os-Saltaneh (Persian Minister in London) dated 1309. (A.H.) Concerning the activities of Malkan Khan and Liyyid Gamal-od-Din against the Persian government in London. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 87. Mohammad Ali-Shah (Shah of Iran after his abdication from throne): Complaining about the late arrival of money. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 88. Ahmad Qavam to Dr. Ghani: Concerning the construction of a hospital in Lahidjan. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 89. Writer unknown to Saheb Jam: Complaining of illness (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 90. Haji Mohtashem-os-Saltaneh to Dr. Ghani: An invitation to his house. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 91. Ali Soheili (then minister of foreign affairs) to Dr. Ghani: Expressing condolences. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 92. Malek-ol-Mutakkalemin (a famous revolutionary and writer): An interpretation of a few verses of the Koran. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 93. Abol Hassan Djelve (a poet) to Abdol Ali Mirza: Concerning the book of Alfiyeh. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 94. Nazem-ol-Atteba to Aqa Usof, the merchant: Requesting him to send 100 tumans. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 95. Nazem-ol-Atteba: A note on Persian grammar (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 96. The Same: Notions on historical and medical problems. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 97. The Same. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 98. The Same. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 99. The handwriting of Haji Mulla Hadi Sabzevazi (A famous Persian philosopher): Concerning the donation of two days water supply to divinity students. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 100. The minister of foreign affairs' agent in Khorassan to the ministry: Concerning the personal affairs of Mirza Hosein Khan. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 101. The handwriting of Sabuzi Esfahani (a contemporary poet) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 102. Jiyyid Nasrolla Taqavi to Dr. Ghani: Recommendation for Dr. Alavi. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 103. Ali Khan Zahir-od-Dowleh (Governor of Mazanderan) dated 1278 (A.H.). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 104. Nazem-ol-Atteba: A note about Ali-ebne-Abbass (a 4th century physician) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 105. Kazemzadeh Iranshahr to Dr. Ghani (May 27, 1938): Thanking him for the book of Avicenna. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 106. Pirzadeh to the Shah: Requesting monetary help. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 107. The marriage certificate of Amir Azam and Esmat Khanom. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 108. Haji Molla Sultan Ali Gonabadi to Hosein Ali Shirazi: Informing him of the receipt of a book. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 109. The handwriting of Haji Aqa Mohammad Najm Abadi. (a famous mujtahed). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 110. Malek-al-Kalam: Some poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 111. Moin-od-Dowleh Sheibami: some poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 112. Iradj Mirza Jalal-ol-Molk (a famous poet of the period of Persian revolution): some poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 113. Malek-ol-Kolam Sharqi: some poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 114. Mirza Hosein Khan Badi (a poet): poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 115. Vahid Dastgerdi (poet): some poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 116. Tului Araqi (poet): poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 117. Sorushe (poet): poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 118. Ghomam Hamadani (poet): poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 119. Ebrat Naim (poet): Poetry (page from a book) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 120. Adib Beizai Kashani (poet): Poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 121. Malek-ol-Kalam Shargi (poet): Poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 122. Adib Beizai Kashani (poet): Poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 123. Aqa Sheikh Hadi Birjandi to (addressee unknown): Concerning his poetry. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 124. Sorush (Poet): poetry. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 125. The handwriting of Aqa Hosein Nadjm Abadi (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 126. Aqa Sheikh Hadi Birjandi to (addressee unknown): Concerning his biography. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 127. Nasyr Divan Fozuni Kermanshahi: some poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 128. Mirza Nemate Rouzani to (addressee unknown): Concerning his family affairs. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 129. Sheikh Ahmad Shalroodi to Amir Azam: Concerning the necessity of preventing the export of wheat. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 130. The Same: Concerning the plight of some tradssmen. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 131. Siyyid Hassan Modarres to(addreseee unknown): Recommending two persons as candidates for the Parliament. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 132. Ebrahim Khan Samiáº½to Mohammad Hassan: Concerning the management of his estates. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 133. Karim Dad Khan Nardini to Mirza Mehdi Khan Birjandi: Concerning a lot of land in Birjand. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 134. Sho-os-Saltaneh (Mohammad All Shah's brother) to the minister of Court: Concerning the sale of a garden. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 135. Firuz Mirza Nosrat-od-Dowleh to his son Mozaffar Firuz: Inquiring after his health and that of his family. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 136. Sho-os-Saltaneh to the Minister of Court: Concerning the sale of a garden. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 137. Mostofi-ol-Mamalek to the Crown Prince: Concerning Ehtessab-ol-Molk. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 138. Mostofi-ol-Mamalek to (addressee unknown): The same. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 139. Orders concerning the working days of the employees of the various sections of the court in Azaraijan. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 140. Esmail Khan Momtaz-od-Dowleh to (addressee unknown): Concerning family affairs. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 141. Writer unknown to Haji Sad-od-Dowleh: Concerning some orders given to Molla Bashi (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 142. The handwriting of Haji's Sheikh Hadi: The sura of Ankabut from the Koran. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 143. Not identified. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 144. The letter from Dr. E. Brown to Mohammad Kazem Khorassani, dated 1329 A.H. Concerning the danger of the rivalry between the Bakhtiari and Qashqai tribes and asking Khorassani to advise the tribes to stop the rivalry. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 145. Mirza Aqa Khan Nuri (Chancellor) to Aziz Khan Sarda: Concerning the signing of a secret treaty between Iran and Russia. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 146. A letter of Aqa Khan Nuzi to Aziz Khan Sardar: Concerning the same treaty. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 147. Mohammad Kazem Khorassani: In reply to an inquiry concerning the necessity of the Parliament in Iran. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 148, 149 and 150. The treaty between Iran and Russia concerning the neutrality of Iran during the Russo-Turkish War. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 151. Mirza Ali Khan Amin-od-Dowleh (Chancellor) to Naser-ed-Din Shah: Criticizing the administration of the government. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- SERIES II
  - 152. A translation of the telegram of the English Foreign Minister to the English Minister in Tehran, dated 1325: Concerning the invasion of the Persian borders by the Ottoman army and the discussion on this score with the Russian ambassador in Istanbul. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 153. English Minister in Tehran to Farmanfarma, dated 1325. A translation of two telegrams received from London, are being sent (Concerning the border problems between Iran and Turkey.) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 154. Farmanfarma to Mohammad Ali Shah presenting a rug and 500 Tumans. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 155. An order of Naser-ed-Din Shah, dated 1268, concerning the appointment of Sultan Murad Mirza to the governorship of Khorasan. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 156. A piece of the handwriting of Teimurtash: Concerning the question of justice. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 157. A piece of handwriting of Farmanfarma vowing friendship to Amin-od-Dowleh if he will remain loyal to Mohammad Ali Shah and the Qajar dynasty. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 158. A piece of handwriting of Abul Qasem concerning a philosophical problem. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 159. Farmanfarma to his wife Ezatod-Dowleh: Sending a message to Mohammad Ali Shah via her, advising the Shah to be more careful in giving his orders and complaining that the Shah is so busy with people that there is no time to discuss secret problems with him. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 160. Mossadeq-os-Saltaneh (Dr. Mossadeq) to Farmanfarma concerning the court situation of Mohammad Ali Shah and the Parliament. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 161. The rest of the above letter. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 162. A telegram of Amin-os-Soltan to Farmanfarma--dated 1325(A.H.): Concerning the appointment of Farmanfarma to the governorship of Azarbaijan. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 163. Mohammad Ali Shah to Haji Mirz Rafi Khan, dated 1325 A.H. saying that he has left all his furniture in Azarbaijan to Farmanfarma. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 164. Mohammad Ali Shah to Farmanfarma saying that the furniture was given to him as a gift and money was expected, but since he has sent some, it will be accepted. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 165. An order of Mohammad Ali Shah dated 1325 A.H. concerning the appointment of Farmanfarma to command of the Zuleh tribe. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 166. An order of Mohammad Ali Shah, 1325 (A.H.) concerning the appointment of Farmanfarma to the Ministry of Justice. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 167. An order of Mohammad Ali Shah, 1325 (A.H.) concerning the appointment of Farmanfarma to the Governorship of Azarbaijan. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 168. Reza Shah to Feridoon Jam (his son-in-law) dated 15 Khordad 1322 A.H. criticizing the character of Persians. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 169. A copy of the concession for the construction of highways and railroads in different parts of Iran to Ein-od-Dawleh, Moshir-od Dawleh, and others. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 170. Mohammad Hassan Mirza (heir to the throne) to Farmanfarma concerning an incident on the Turkish border. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 171. A piece of Farmanfarma's handwriting concerning his loyalty to Mohammad Ali Shah and the Qajar dynasty. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 172. Zel-os-Sultan to Farmanfarma--dated Shaval, 1324 A.H.: Complaining of illness and stating his decision to go to Europe. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 173. A letter from Ommul Khaqan (Mozafar-ed-Din Shah's wife) to Farmanfarma (her son-in-law) reproaching him for leaving his wife at home and marrying women in other places. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 174. Ommul Khaqan to Ezat-os-Saltaneh (her daughter and Farmanfarma's wife) Concerning a transaction and other family affairs. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 175. An order of Naser-ed-Din Shah, dated Moharram, 1268. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 176. A piece of handwriting of Mohammad Taqi Mirza-od-Dowleh (Naser-od-Din Shah's brother): several Arabic verses. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 177. Hassan Ali Khan Garusi addressed to his brother recommending Abdul Ali Niknam and requesting the return of his property. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 178. Mirza Abol Qasem Qaen Maqam addressee unknown--Expressing gratitude for being remembered. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 179. Ron-od-Dowleh to Naser-ed-Din Shah. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 180. The same. Concerning the marriage of his son Nasrullah Mirza with Sharaf-od-Dowleh. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 181. Written by unknown to Heshmat-od-Sultan the mayor of Quchan. Concerning the city's affairs and borders. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 182. Foroughi Zoka ol Mulk to Dr. Ghani sending him several books. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 183. Mirza Ali Khan addressee unknown complaining that he is out of favor and stating that he is ready to hand in Governments accounts. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 184. Mozaffar-ed-Din Shah to Rok-od-Dowleh (in his handwriting). Asking about his health. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 185. Ein-od-Dowleh to Qaen-Maqem ol-Molk Rashti (Rafi) on the occasion of the death of Shariet Madar expressing his condolences. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 186. The secretary of the heir to the throne to Rafi dated 17 Shahrisar 1306. Concerning the health and the education of the prince. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 187. Kam-ran Mirza to Rafi--Expressing condolences on the occasion of the death of Shariet Madar. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 188. Shor-os-Soltaneh (Mohammad Ali Shah's brother) to Rafi: Expressing his sorrow on the illness of Rafi and discussing the situations arising from the war. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 189. Sad-od-Dowleh to Rafi: Concerning the suit of Mokhber-os-Soltaneh and his nephews. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 190. Sam-Sam-os-Soltaneh Bakltia to Rafi concerning the presentation of his views to the members of the Cabinet when they meet. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 191. Zahir-od-Dowleh to Rafi: Recommending Yazdan Verdi Khan. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 192. Sepahdar to Rafi: Expressing his friendship. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 193. Taymurtash to Rafi--Recommending Mirza Mohammad Khan. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 194. Ala ol Mulk to Rafi--Concerning a leave for his son. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 195. Sepahsalar TonKaboni to Rafi expressing friendship. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 196. Sepahsalar to Rafi--the same. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 197. Saad-od-Dowleh to Rafi: Concerning the ruling of the court on his financial affairs. (Box 1, Folder 7)